There are infinite combinations of bugs that
can result in account takeovers and the truth
is that we will never be able to test for all
of them. So to learn which techniques actually
make people money, I studied $1.3 million dollars worth of
bug bounty account takeover reports and I studied
them. In this video, I will show you what are the
most common ways to takeover an account. Enjoy!
I will start in reverse order from the least
common method that I found to the most common
one and the least common one was clickjacking with
only two reports and this is a vulnerability class
I had absolutely zero respect some time ago and I
actually gained it when I was covering this bug.
When I was covering the Metamask clickjacking
which allowed to transfer funds to anyone. So
this report is not part of this case study
but it's an excellent example of an actual
clickjacking attack with a real serious impact.
In this case, here is a nice blog post. There
are three different write-ups here which usually
is a huge pain for me, it's usually the hardest
write-ups to understand when doing this case study
when it's like a mass write-up of a few bugs.
There are often details missing and things like
that but this is actually a really good one by
Renwa. No idea how to read this. And we had this
clickjacking attack. Here is a nice visualization.
Clickjacking becomes impactful when the victim
only has to click a button to confirm some action.
In this case, the victim has to confirm changing
the email address. I assumed that the attacker had
a way to somehow fill this but the victim has to
click change email and, obviously, normally they
will not do this because they see that it's
changing the email to someone else's address.
But you can manipulate with transparent iframes
and put this with transparency and put this in
front so that the user actually sees on the
website something that's under this iframe
but this is invisible. Then, the victim has to
click the button and then this way they change
the email of the victim and they can then change
their passwords. Usually, for clickjacking proof
of concepts, it's enough to just show something
like click here. In the real attack, obviously,
you would have to create some social engineering
idea on how to get a user to click something but
it shouldn't be that difficult. A cookie pop-up or
an advertisement pop-up should should do the job.
So this is the clickjacking
this is the first category.
The next vulnerability class is pre-account
takeover with 3 reports in the case study
this bug class is a bit controversial because
some companies do not reward this vulnerability
class some people say it shouldn't be rewarded
in my opinion this is a very good example of a
low risk attack with quite a good impact
actually but very unlikely exploitation.
The way this the pre-account takeover works is
somehow you have to register either a particular
username or a particular email and then when the
victim comes to the website and wants to use this
website your accounts kind of get merged the one
way it can happen is if the victim logs in using
Facebook but before you created an account
using the email using victims unconfirmed
email and then when they log in with Facebook
using the same email your accounts get merged
and you still have access using the password
to the account that the victim actually uses
so it is not an easy attack to perform but in my
opinion it's a very good example of a low risk
vulnerability that should be rewarded because the
impact is there in this case we have one report in
in github and the way it works is
quite interesting because you have to
create an account obviously and then you have
to remove this account but when you remove the
account your session still was still a valid
session for an account that doesn't exist but
it was still valid and later when someone would
create an account with the same username your
session would become the session of the new user
so it sounds like a very unlikely attack because
you not only have to know the username of the
victim that will start using npmjs because it was
the vulnerable website but you also have to still
keep this session alive and I'm not sure how long
the session is alive or how can you keep it alive
but it sounds like a really difficult attack to
perform but it was rewarded four thousand dollars
of bounty so quite a nice quite a nice reward
Next we'll step to first bug class that has
more reports and is more has more variety in it
because when I do this case studies I always
try to maintain a good level good balance
between being too specific and too broad and
sometimes I just have to merge things together.
Now we come to direct authentication bypass which
just means that the authentication mechanism was
in some way broken. One example of a bug like this
is this one it's a one hundred thousand dollars
bug in Apple which is a lot and is actually a
super super simple bug that pretty much this is
this is what it is there is just a request with
an email and in the response there is a token
which you can use to log in and that's pretty much
the bug. Unfortunately the gold of this write-up
is hidden behind this path because probably if
it would be a path that's normally used someone
would detect it already because it's quite a
straightforward bug so it's very interesting
what's this path and and how did the hunter find
it but this was this is the highest paid report
from the whole case study. I'm
not surprised that the impact is absolutely huge
but this is the one. This is another one. It
was a common scenario where you could copy the
cookie from one application to another and it
would work. This particular report I covered on
my channel already I will link the video in the
description. And the way it works is there was
there were two different applications on
this using the same machine and turned out
that they use the same secret for signing the
cookie or encrypting the cookie or whatever
and you could log in to one website using account
from another website using the session from
another website there was also some SSRFs here
not not interesting today. It's interesting for
me because it's an attack I don't think
I've ever tried to do it I've never like tried to
copy a cookie from one application to another and
apparently I should. Here's this absolutely the
same situation in Starbucks where the Singapore
website worked in another website I believe
KU2SAC whatever whatever this
worked with Starbucks Singapore
there was also at least one other
report where you could copy a cookie
from one country website to another maybe to
a Starbucks as well I don't remember. Other
kinds of bypasses because there were a lot of
bugs like like these these two types where you
would copy the cookie or you would just get the
token basically what happened with Apple.
There were also some reports where you would somehow
break the flow of authentication so I don't know
there are 3 requests of
authentication you would send the second one
instead of the first one or something like this.
This is this it was also quite quite a common
situation but I'm showing you this report to tell
you to that there is no vulnerability class called
response manipulation there is no vulnerability
class response manipulation and if you use it
in write apps or whatever please stop response
manipulation is something you can use to help you
detect the vulnerability but essentially what
happens is usually you do something like this
you change error=false to error=true or success=false to success=true and the application that
the client-side JavaScript in your browser thinks
that the request was successful so it sends the
next request whatever it is. So if you change the
response is not actually response manipulation the
bug here. The bug is that the next request that
gets sent does not have authentication check or
authorization check and this is the vulnerability.
It's in the next request that's that's vulnerable
not the one that you change the response to so
please just stop stop using response manipulation
as a title of the bug. Of course, it's a perfectly
valid strategy to look for bugs. Personally,
I mostly use this when I'm testing like
client-side code for XSS or whatever
most of the time when when the situation
like this when I have a flow that's
that has a few different requests I prefer to
first just go through the flow legitimately
with my credentials or whatever and then
like send the same request with different
cookies or whatever if that's possible I would
prefer to do this over changing the response
and hoping that the client-side JS will
do the job for me but in some situations you
have to do this but remember it's not actually
this request that's vulnerable it's the next one
and one final type of report that I saw a
few times was just insecure session cookie
and in no report I saw an actually advanced
cryptographic attack for these cookies. It was
usually something very simple. Sometimes, it was
just an ID or like in this case just a very short
string that can be brute-forced I didn't find
any disclosed report where it would be actually
like cryptographically complex stuff breaking the
cookie so so when you're testing session ID when
it's long just just assume that you can't modify
it then prefer to like come up with an application
from which you can copy the whole cookie rather
than hoping that you can magically like bypass it.
So these are a few types of bugs that I saw a few
times that caught my attention that resulted in
direct authentication bypass. Of course, this
this video is about the free chapter of the
case study. The whole case study is a part of
a BBRE Premium subscription you can access the
whole article there I also this time included a
checklist with things that you should check for
when looking for account takeovers I think
it is is really nice and really helpful so
make sure to check this out. You also get access
to all these reports so if you want to study them
more carefully or you're looking for a particular
exploit in in your application you're testing
just open all those reports and
find the one relevant to you.
In the meanwhile we'll step to the second most
popular way to take over the account which is
SSO takeover and take a look at what happens here
take a look I interviewed Youssef Sammouda a few
weeks ago. He's the author of many of these bugs
in Facebook and I knew he has a lot of reports
in Facebook but I had no idea he has that many
like all the links here that say ysamm
it's his bugs in in Facebook and take a look at
the bounties it's absolutely insane and to be
honest these reports completely skewed all the
statistics in the in this case study I also did
in the in the Premium chapters like a breakthrough
of client-side server-side vulnerabilities type of
interaction and average bounties for for these
different reports just look completely ruined by
how many great $40,000 reports Youssef submitted
to to Facebook of course I encourage you to to
listen to to the podcast that that I've recorded
with Youssef it was very interesting one and he
just explained how did this how did this happen
so stepping into two concrete examples of reports
the SSO takeover in most cases if not all
cases means that you can leak the code the
authentication code that's part of the flow I will
not go into the detail of the whole flow because
it deserves a video on its own and I actually
created a video on its own about this very
report on your screen right now which allowed to
take over Facebook account if someone used Gmail
to log in it's quite a complex one and to be
honest I had there's no doubt in my mind that
Youssef deserves all these great reports because
none of these reports is straightforward there are
always a few steps there is always a chain some
some magic trick and here as well we have multiple
steps for this attack to work it's not easy so
in this case you could just leave the code and
take over the account but this is just the the end
result for example here take a look at the at this
at this trick that he used here there was a
redirect URI but when he would send redirect URI
as an array with the zero of index it would
confuse the server side and client side
and the server would verify a different redirect
URI parameter then the client would redirect to
because one of these components considered this to
be the redirect URI there was also normal redirect
URI and there was inconsistency in how do they
treat this strange input which resulted in open
redirect which resulted in quite a typical account
takeover so very one of very nice tricks this also
I think I've never tried in my life I tried
some I usually try some type of HTTP parameter
pollution but never this this variation so I will
definitely start start doing it the next time
I'm hunting here is another report I really liked
also some of these account takeovers happened due
to CSRFs in some part of the flow you could either
add your Apple account or your Facebook account to
to victims normal account or do something else
and this happens for for various reasons usually
there is just no CSRF protection but I really
like this attack it's in in GitHub by Teddy Katz
and the way it works is or rather the reason it
works is that when you would send when you would
click this button to authorize a user a request
would be sent to /login/oauth/authorize
this is this is the way it's defined in short
so you have the route you have methods that
that you want to route to this particular
controller and inside the controller you have a
code like this and it should be quite obvious what
happens because you only route two methods here
and now you check if request is GET we get
to this code so if it's GET we just serve
the authorization page HTML so nothing happens
no sensitive action is done nothing is modified
but else all this flow happens which should
happen when the POST is sent here and it should be
straightforward because we have two methods here
GET and POST so if it's get we go here if it's
not GET it should only mean that it's POST but it
doesn't mean that it's POST because there's also
HEAD method. HEAD method is like a GET but without
body and no developers actually actively supported
the HEAD method unless they absolutely have to the
way frameworks work is they treat HEAD method the
same way as they should GET just the difference
is that at the end they drop the body and only
send headers because HTTP HEAD method means that
you should only get headers but this means that
when the request is routed here a HEAD method
will also be routed to this controller
but the HEAD method will not get through this if
statement it will not satisfy this check so it
will land in the else block and for HEAD method
the CSRF protection is not enabled by default
and in this case you could just send parameters in
the URL as the URL parameters after the question
mark and it worked I actually used this trick
very recently actually maybe most of you don't
know about it because I don't speak about it
very often but I play CTFs in justCutTheFish
and recently we organized our CTF I
created one task and I used this very trick
to as not the whole task as half of the task
and I actually had a different idea about the
task and last last minute I had to change it
because I saw too many unintended solutions
and I was actually doing this case study and I
saw this report and I thought that this is a great
thing to introduce in the challenge I link the
challenge in the description because the source
code of the challenge is available or will be
available so you can you can try and solve it
as much as I saw loads of all of reports there
was only one single report with SAML. I only saw
this one from uber from 2017 where it will be the
most basic SAML attack where just the assertion
wouldn't be verified so you can pretty much send
anything there I was really really surprised by
this because I thought that there will be I knew
that there will be more Oauth vulnerabilities than
SAML but I had no idea the difference will be that
huge and it really is the only one that I found
which is very very surprising to me and if you are
a developer if you're watching this as a developer
maybe think about using SAML will because
apparently it is easier to implement then Oauth
and here it's like the more typical vulnerability
for 2023 because no longer the redirect URI
seems to be vulnerable to open redirect when
you can just put the attackers URL or Burp
collaborator URL and leak the code this way but
often like in the Youssef's report to Facebook
with Gmail like in the the famous blog post by
Frans Rosen you can still somehow control at least
the path of the request like in this case this is
a report from from 2023 you can't you don't have a
full open redirect to to just send the code to you
but there is path traversal which allows you to
make the code be sent to another website
within the target website and then
in this case using Google Analytics you
had the way to exfiltrate the code
and this is like the modern way of account
takeovers and this is very very prevalent
and now with that said let's go to the most common
way to take over a client which was to change
victims password it was the most common however
the average bounty is much lower but this is in
big part due to the amount of Facebook
reports the intuition would tell me this will be
the more impactful one because usually this does
not require user interaction and because these are
mostly server-side attacks and in the Oauth takeover
you always need the interaction so it's always a
little bit lower severity here a very common
common attack that that I saw in this category
category had to do with OTP codes and actually a
very simple I would even say almost a naive attack
would be to just brute force the OTP codes in this
case we have $50,000 bounty to Microsoft and the
hunter was just able to to brute force seven digit
code usually these are not as naive brute forces
from a single IP address usually these involve
renting multiple cloud computing instances to
attack the server from different IP addresses
and often hunters just include some estimations
or some calculations of how many codes they can
predict in what time it also depends on the the
lifespan of the OTP code but there were a lot of
a lot of bugs like this there was also Instagram
I think it was it was one of these attacks which I saw big companies making mistakes
the OTP codes were in a lot of situations there
were also very interesting reports like this
one I also covered it on my channel very early so
if you watch this video it will probably be much
lower quality but it was also some kind of strange
order of signing up changing the email having some
race conditions in in the timing of where is
the password address and links and or whatever
in this case you had to
change the email and send the
I think confirmation email in the correct
time and you could take over the account
it's a report by by Ron Chan I actually missed the
guy because he's not hunting anymore and I loved
his reports so Ron if you're watching this please
come back to hunting because I need your reports
to have interesting videos there were also simpler
simpler bugs but these often happened in lower
lower bounty this usually had lower bounties which
means they were in smaller applications here we
have avatar whatever this is I have no idea what
avatar is and just this is the attack just the
password dressed request has new password
has no old password and has an email
so it's like very straightforward thing to
do to to just change the email to the victim
and and it worked and there
were a lot of reports like this
but often or always it wasn't big companies it was
even though the attack has great impact because
it's it just allows you to take over anyone's
account instantly without the interaction
these weren't often super high bounties in this
case it's four and a half thousand which is on
the which is actually quite quite good but there
were a lot like one thousand five hundred dollars
for these reports another thing that was
was present a few times was aws cognito
on the ctf I've mentioned my friends had a
task with with cognito I will also link this
I'm not sure if this is online or not but you
can at least see the source code this is this
allows the developer to like outsource the the
authentication to to the service from Amazon
and you can also interact with with cognito using
AWS CLI which which can be a really nice attack
and the last type of vulnerabilities which I
want to talk about is host header poisoning
this is also very much related to to changing
the the email because in the in the case study
I say that the way to take over account is
to change victims password but some of these
attacks actually resulted in changing the email
or changing the phone number and only then the
attacker would have to reset the password
from from there so it were was not always
directly connected functionalities to password
reset but they resulted in in password reset as
I've said the next chapter of the case study
was about the root cause of the bug where I
where I dig deep into what was the actual reason
for the bug to happen and the way I wrote it is as
a checklist for things to check so so if you
are a member of BBRE Premium check this out
but in this report as I've mentioned this is very
much related to the password reset functionality
because the way it works is you change the value
of the host header and then the password reset
link has your malicious host in the link to
me personally this is the attack I I think
I would barely reward or I would reward really
low because it requires the victim to click this
link even though they didn't reset the password
and and not notice the domain which I think is
even less likely than the pre-account takeover
scenario that works and here it was rewarded$2,000
If you enjoyed this one chapter of the
case study I guarantee that you will learn much
more when you finally join BBRE Premium and get
access to the full article, the checklist, and the
database of those reports. In the meantime,
if you want to listen to our podcast with
Youssef, it's on your screen at the moment.
For now, thank you for watching and goodbye!